<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The restoring of fallen brethren containing the substance of two sermons on Gal. VI, 1, 2 preached at the performance of publick penance by certain criminals on the Lord's-day, usually called mid-Lent Sunday, 1696, in the parish church of Old-Swinford in Worcestershire / by Simon Ford.</title>
            <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11213637</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11213637</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39923)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:83)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The restoring of fallen brethren containing the substance of two sermons on Gal. VI, 1, 2 preached at the performance of publick penance by certain criminals on the Lord's-day, usually called mid-Lent Sunday, 1696, in the parish church of Old-Swinford in Worcestershire / by Simon Ford.</title>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RESTORING OF <hi>Fallen Brethren:</hi> Containing, the Subſtance of Two SERMONS, On <hi>Gal.</hi> VI. 1, 2. Preached at the Performance of PUBLICK PENANCE, By certain CRIMINALS, On the <hi>Lord's-day,</hi> uſually called <hi>Mid-Lent Sunday;</hi> 1696.</p>
            <p>In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Old-Swinford</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> D. D. and Rector there.</p>
            <p>With a Preface by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s-Church-Yard. 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE following Sermons is of an extraordinary Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; being Preached by the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, at the Performance of a publick Penance, enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſeveral Criminals of his Pariſh. If others of the Clergy would follow ſo good an Example, and do what in them lies to uphold the ſmall Remainders of ancient Diſcipline among us; it would bring more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to our Church, and the Religion Eſtabliſhed among us, than the warmeſt Diſputes for our Conſtitution, without regard to the Practiſe of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am not inſenſible, what ſcandalous Imputations our Eccleſiaſtical Courts lie under; but I deſire thoſe who are Concerned, to conſider, in how much better Reputation they might be, if the Management of them were more carefully look'd into, and brought to that Order which the Law of the Land Allows; and the ancient Canons, and common Rules of Juſtice and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty require. And ſince thoſe Proſecutions are now taken off by Law, which made the loudeſt Noiſe and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt them; I hope we may let the World ſee, that what Power is left in our Hands, is Employed</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:46829:3"/> 
               <hi>for the beſt Ends,</hi> viz. the Puniſhment of evil Doers; and the Encouragement of thoſe that do well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I fear there are ſome who had rather have Faults continued, that they might ſtill have occaſion to complain, than uſe any Endeavours to Reform the Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Committed in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know no Courts, but are liable to Abuſes; but there is a difference to be made, between ſuch as ariſe from the Rules and Orders of the Court, and ſuch which come only from the perſonal Faults of thoſe who are employ'd in them. As to the former, the Methods of Proceeding in theſe Courts, are of as great Antiquity, at leaſt; as of any other Courts of greateſt Eſteem among us: The Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws have the ſame Advantage of Cuſtom and long Obſervation, which any other Laws of the Land have; but as to the particular Proceedings oſ ſeveral Courts, the Rules are generally known, and certain, and agreeable to the Laws, and not left to any arbitrary Methods. But where the Faults lie only in the Perſons; I hope that upon any juſt Complaints, effectual Care will be taken to Puniſh the Tranſgreſſors, and to prevent the like for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the General, and moſt ſenſible Complaint hath been, that Money, which Governs the World too much, hath ſo great an Influence on theſe Courts, that any Criminal Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may be excuſed from doing Penance, by a pecuniary Commutation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether there hath been any juſt Occaſion formerly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for any Complaint of that Nature, is out of my reach to enquire; but I hope there hath not of late been any Cauſe for it. Eſpecially, ſince by His Majeſties</hi> Injunctions <hi>N.</hi> 17. No Commutation of Penance is to be made, but by expreſs Order and Directions of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop himſelf; which ſhall be declared in open Court. <hi>And I hope theſe</hi> Injunctions <hi>will not be like new Laws made for Repairs of High-ways; which often leave them as bad as they find them. If there have been ſcandalous Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, which through the Neglect of the Clergy, or the proper Officers have not been Preſented, let the blame lie, where it ought to do; the Eccleſiaſtical Courts have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be charged with other Mens Faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt ſay it for the Honour of the worthy Author of theſe Sermons, that he took care to have the Court duly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Miſcarriages and Crimes Committed in his Pariſh: whereupon, the Offenders, who performed the Penance, ſubmitted to the Sentence of the Court for it. Which was accordingly done in the moſt publick manner; and he Preached a very ſeaſonable and uſeful Diſcourſe now Printed, relating to the Occaſion. And that it may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the good Ends for which it was deſigned, is my hearty Deſire and Prayer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ed. Wigorn.</signed>
               <dateline>Worceſter, <date>Apr. 8. 97.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46829:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GALAT. VI. 1. 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren, if any man be overtaken in a fault; ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch an one in the ſpirit of meekneſs: conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bear ye one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfil the law of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALthough (dearly beloved,) I have of late been deeply affected with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and ſecretly <hi>Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> upon occaſion of the Ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſcandalous Sin, adviſeth that Church to do, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2.) for the late <hi>Fornications,</hi> and filthy <hi>Uncleanneſſes,</hi> that have been committed in this Neighbourhood, by ſo many Perſons as are now juſtly under Cenſure of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judicatory:</hi> yet am I, at laſt, (on the other ſide) not a little <hi>comforted,</hi> that my good Adviſe to divers of the <hi>Criminals,</hi> who now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before you, has had ſo good effect, as to render them willing, notwithſtanding all the <hi>Diſcouragements,</hi> which have. I doubt, been given them by either their obſtinate <hi>Fellow-ſinners,</hi> or factious <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from this <hi>Church,</hi> and it's <hi>Diſcipline,)</hi> to preſent themſelves here, as <hi>Penitents,</hi> to perform the <hi>Penance</hi> enjoyned them; and thereby, to give me occaſion, to inſtruct you all in thoſe Points relating
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46829:5"/> to this Exerciſe of <hi>Church-diſcipline,</hi> concerning which, except upon ſuch an occaſion, you might not have heard from this <hi>Pulpit;</hi> and ſo, either through Ignorance, or prejudicated Opinion, have been led into unworthy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions concerning it.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Text</hi> I have choſen, I think, will afford me Grounds ſufficient for the handling all the <hi>Heads,</hi> to which, on this Occaſion I intend to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>You may therefore herein obſerve theſe three <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. A <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> (that <hi>Chriſtian Brethren may be overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſuch Faults as render them like Members out of joynt, in the Body of Chriſt, to which they belong: and ſo need (to prevent their farther Corruption, and danger of becoming Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grened, and in the Iſſue, cut off) the charitable Endeavours of their Fellows to ſet them in Joynt again.)</hi> For ſo the Word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which we render <hi>(reſtore,)</hi> does import.</p>
            <p n="2">II. A <hi>poſitive Duty</hi> incumbent on the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Brethren,</hi> (upon ſuch a <hi>Suppoſal,</hi> actually coming to paſs, in any Chriſtian Society:) to wit, <hi>(to uſe all Chriſtian Means they can, thus to reſtore ſuch diſlocated or diſabled Members to their former Soundneſs.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to the better performance of which <hi>Duty,</hi> there are <hi>two</hi> Particulars obſervable, under this Head in the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. The <hi>Deſcription</hi> of the <hi>Perſons</hi> who are to act in this charitable Work, <hi>(they that are Spiritual;)</hi> which Phraſe what it means, you ſhall be informed anon, when I come to that <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Aſſignation</hi> of the <hi>manner</hi> how this <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Duty</hi> is to be performed <hi>(in the Spirit of Meekneſs.)</hi> and that heightned to ſuch a degree of <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> as gives them a kind of <hi>fellow-feeling</hi> in the <hi>pains</hi> thoſe <hi>diſlocated</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46829:5"/> 
               <hi>Members</hi> undergo, called <hi>(v. 2.) (bearing one anothers brudens.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> (and <hi>laſtly) two</hi> proper <hi>Motives</hi> to induce <hi>them</hi> to the Performance of this <hi>Duty,</hi> in the <hi>manner</hi> directed.</p>
            <p>(I.) <hi>One,</hi> taken from a <hi>confiderate Senſibleneſs</hi> of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon humane Frailty:</hi> Hazarding the <hi>ſound Members</hi> to fall, and bruiſe themſelves at one time or other, upon like <hi>Tentations</hi> as occaſioned the Harms the <hi>fallen Brethren</hi> had reeeived. And herein 'tis ſpecially remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (by a kind of <hi>Apoſtrophe,)</hi> applies himſelf to each Particular of the <hi>Spiritualty,</hi> whom heex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to this Charity; wiſhing every of them to <hi>conſider</hi> his own Frailty, and Danger thereby, in the Words, <hi>(leſt thou alſo be tempted.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(II.) The <hi>other,</hi> from the Obedience they owe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Law, in a ſpecial manner, requiring this at their Hands: So that by thus Meckly and Compaſſionately taking part of their Brethrens <hi>Burdens, they (fulfil the law of Chriſt.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all, which I intend to diſcourſe in order.</p>
            <p>I. Of the <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> which is here laid down as the Ground of the <hi>Duty;</hi> which contains in it this <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That true members of the body of Chriſt, are liable to be overtaken in ſuch faults, as may ſorely bruiſe and cruſh them, and render them, for the time they lie under the guilt and pain of them, like diſlocated Members in the natural Body, and (do need to prevent their farther Corruption and danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingg angrened, and in the Iſſue cut off to need the charitable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of their Fellows, to ſet them in joynt again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to be a <hi>Saint,</hi> whilſt here below in this Eſtate of <hi>Imperfection,</hi> does not diveſt any one totally of the <hi>Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Humanity;</hi> nor does the <hi>Seed of God</hi> in us that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news our Nature, ſecure us from a Poſſibility of <hi>ſinning</hi> altogether; but only from <hi>Sinning to Death,</hi> i. e. Sinning at that rate that <hi>hardned habitual Sinners</hi> do, which the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which denotes a <hi>profeſſed pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46829:6"/> of ſin,</hi> which, by indiſpoſition, bars the Door as to Recovery by <hi>Repentance,</hi> and ſo makes a Man incapable of <hi>Pardon,</hi> as appears by comparing 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 8, 9. with 5. 16, 17, 18. But as to <hi>Acts</hi> of Sin committed through <hi>Surreption</hi> and <hi>Surpriſe,</hi> by the over-prevalency of a <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Tentation,</hi> not foreſeen and provided againſt, he himſelf tells us, that whoever <hi>denies ſuch Sins to be in him,</hi> or affirms that he is ſo Priviledged, as not to be capable of having ſo Sinned; he is <hi>a liar, deceiving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> with vain Notions of an <hi>unattainable perfection,</hi> and the <hi>Truth is not in him,</hi> Chap. 1. 8, 10. And indeed, if this kind of <hi>Sinleſsneſs</hi> were attainable by any one here, the <hi>Apoſtles Motive</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> (to induce the moſt <hi>Spiritual</hi> Men to <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> in <hi>reſtoring</hi> fallen <hi>Brethren,</hi> upon the conſideration of their own <hi>Frailty,)</hi> would be to no purpoſe; as to ſuch a Perſon, as pretends to it; who might hence juſtifie his greateſt <hi>Inſolencies</hi> againſt <hi>Offenders,</hi> as proceeding from <hi>one</hi> that by his <hi>Priviledge</hi> is exempt from that Conſideration, on which the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>Duty</hi> is preſſed. He ſuppoſeth therefore here, that the holieſt Man may be obnoxious to ſuch <hi>Falls,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſeen <hi>Stumbling-blocks,</hi> laid in his way, may occaſion: as the Word, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in the <hi>Original,</hi> properly import.</p>
            <p>And the uſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here makes of this Doctrine, (beſides that which he urges from it, by way of <hi>Motive</hi> to the <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> which in it's proper place will come to be conſidered;) is to exerciſe every one to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider himſelf,</hi> as thus liable to <hi>Temptation;</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be <hi>watchful,</hi> and <hi>look about him,</hi> (as Perſons in a <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon,</hi> beleaguered by an Enemy, are wont to do, about all their <hi>Line,</hi> to ſee where the <hi>Fortifications</hi> are weak, and in ſuch places to ſet the <hi>ſtronger Guard;</hi> which is the true notion of the <hi>Word</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in the <hi>Text;)</hi> where he lies open to a <hi>Temptation,</hi> and fortifie the weak part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46829:6"/> 
               <hi>Satans Stratagems,</hi> and <hi>devices,</hi> that he <hi>get no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over him,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 11.</p>
            <p>And upon this <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> (the <hi>firſt</hi> thing obſervable in the Text) is built the <hi>ſecond,</hi> which we are now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon.</p>
            <p>II. The <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent upon the <hi>Brethren,</hi> (the reſt of the Church,) in the ſuppoſed Caſe, <hi>when any of them is overtaken in a Fault;</hi> to wit, <hi>that they are to (reſtore ſuch an one;)</hi> that is, (as I before told you,) to uſe, (on their parts,) all Chriſtian means that the <hi>wounded Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> may be reduced to <hi>ſoundneſs again:</hi> and ſo capable of performing the <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent on him, and enjoying the <hi>Benefits,</hi> and comfortable <hi>Priviledges</hi> belonging to him, upon the account of his <hi>Memberſhip</hi> in that <hi>holy Society;</hi> and for which, his <hi>preſent wounded Condition</hi> diſables him. For indeed, foul falls do both ways <hi>diſable</hi> a <hi>Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> more, or leſs, according to the different Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he is under, <hi>i. e.</hi> as his <hi>Crime</hi> is either <hi>ſecret,</hi> or <hi>publick; known</hi> only to ſome <hi>one,</hi> or ſome <hi>few;</hi> or <hi>noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> to the <hi>generality</hi> of thoſe he converſeth with; and, as, (if it be notorious,) it is either before the <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judicatory,</hi> or not: And <hi>laſtly,</hi> as, (if it be under their <hi>Cognizance,)</hi> it either is, or is not, advanced ſo far as to <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Sentence.</hi> And according to theſe, and other Circumſtances of the <hi>Criminal;</hi> ſo are the Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be made uſe of for his <hi>Reſtitution</hi> to be varied. And that both as to the <hi>Perſons,</hi> who are employed in that charitable Work, in their ſeveral Capacities and Stations; and the <hi>manner</hi> how they are to act in order to the Accompliſhing it. And <hi>both</hi> theſe, are to be found in the <hi>Text</hi> alſo, as I before told you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Perſons</hi> who are thus to endeavour the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> are here called (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (ye that are <hi>ſpiritual.)</hi> But it is ſtill a Queſtion; <hi>whom the Apoſtle means by this Compellation?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46829:7"/>
            <p>In <hi>Anſwer</hi> whereunto, I ſhall not confine my ſelf to any of the particular Notions of <hi>differing Interpreters;</hi> but make uſe of them all, ſo far as they will admit of a Senſe, as I apprehend moſt agreeable to the deſign of the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, then, I ſuppoſe, the Word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) here uſed, may in a general Notion, include <hi>all the ſound Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church,</hi> who are, in their ſeveral Stations to bear a part in this charitable Office. For the Church, being (in St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Phraſe, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 5.) a ſpiritual Houſe, or Temple.</hi> I know not, why every <hi>ſtone,</hi> or <hi>rafter</hi> of it, may not partake of the Notion of <hi>Spirituality;</hi> eſpecially ſeeing the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> does there call all Chriſtians not only <hi>lively ſtones,</hi> but (in a ſenſe) an <hi>holy Prieſthood,</hi> to <hi>offer up to God ſpiritual Sacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, there is no <hi>Member</hi> of the Church, but when the Fault of any <hi>Fellow-member</hi> comes to his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, he is obliged to contribute, as he lawfully may in his Station, his Endeavours to <hi>restore him:</hi> for no Man is <hi>to ſuffer Sin upon his Brother,</hi> it it lie in his way to <hi>remove it,</hi> Lev. 19. 17. For to do otherwiſe, is, (in Gods own Interpretation) <hi>to hate him in his Heart,</hi> whom he ſees dangerouſly <hi>wounded,</hi> and yet, (as the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite,</hi> in our <hi>Saviours</hi> Parable, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 31, 32.) goes on <hi>the other ſide of the way,</hi> and lets him <hi>lie,</hi> and <hi>periſh</hi> for want of help.</p>
            <p n="2">2.) There is yet a more <hi>reſtrained notion</hi> of the Word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which will alſo very well ſute the deſign of the <hi>Text,</hi> and the State of the <hi>Galatian Church;</hi> and that is that which diſtinguiſheth the <hi>Members</hi> of the Church, who are, in ſome reſpect, <hi>more Spiritual</hi> from others, who are (in compariſon to them,) elſewhere called <hi>Carnal,</hi> and <hi>Babes in Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 15. and 3. 1. And ſo, (ſeeing all the <hi>Members</hi> of the Church are not alike in <hi>Knowledge, Gifts, or Graces;)</hi> they that excell in any of theſe, (or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46829:7"/> 
               <hi>think they do,</hi> in the Phraſe of Ch. 14. 37.) are more eſpecially obliged to this <hi>charitable Office,</hi> as being, or ſuppoſed to be furniſhed with greater ſtore of <hi>ſpiritual Medicaments,</hi> than their <hi>inferiour Brethren.</hi> For the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> tells us, that all theſe <hi>Gifts</hi> wherein one Chriſtian excells another, are beſtowed, (not to capacitate them to <hi>vaunt</hi> and <hi>magnifie</hi> themſelves, and <hi>contemn others,</hi> who in thoſe reſpects are inferiour to them;) but they are all gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>profit withal,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 7. And that the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of them in a way of <hi>Charity,</hi> is the <hi>moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way,</hi> wherein they may be made uſe of, <hi>v.</hi> 31. of the ſame <hi>Chapter.</hi> But alas! it is a thing to be much lamented, that ordinarily, (from the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> downwards to theſe days,) Perſons, who moſt pretend to be extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily <hi>gifted,</hi> (though indeed, they excel only in a few new <hi>Phraſes,</hi> volubility of <hi>Language,</hi> and impudent <hi>Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c.) inſtead of <hi>charitable reſtoring</hi> their <hi>disjoynted Brethren,</hi> moſt uncharitably <hi>reduce</hi> them into erroneous Opinions, and rend the <hi>Body of Chriſt</hi> into divided <hi>Factions,</hi> and <hi>ſeparated Societies;</hi> gathered (too many of them) out of the moſt <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and <hi>Vicious</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> they <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate</hi> from; whoſe <hi>ſpiritual Wounds</hi> they <hi>heal ſlightly,</hi> by perſwading them, that to become their <hi>Proſelites,</hi> will ſufficiently attone for all <hi>former Crimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But then, <hi>(thirdly,)</hi> becauſe whatever Applications <hi>private Perſons</hi> make in kindneſs to their <hi>wounded Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> may poſſibly be inſufficient to effect a Cure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Aſſiſtance of a <hi>skilful Chyrurgeon;</hi> therefore, I muſt tell you, that the word <hi>Spiritual,</hi> here, does yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit alſo of a moſt <hi>reſtrained Senſe;</hi> to wit, as it denotes thoſe, whoſe <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Employment,</hi> is converſant in <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things;</hi> that are the <hi>Teachers, Guides, Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the Church. Including all, from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> downwards, who are inveſted with thoſe <hi>Offices,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the good of their Souls and Spirits of Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46829:8"/> to their Charge. And to <hi>theſe</hi> only, do ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Learned and Reverend <hi>Commentators</hi> (though I think they are therein too <hi>narrow,</hi> as I intimated before) reſtrain the <hi>Senſe</hi> of this <hi>Word</hi> in the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I concur ſo far with them; as to think theſe <hi>principally</hi> meant; <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe, in the <hi>apostolical Times,</hi> the <hi>Chariſmata,</hi> or <hi>ſpecial Gifts of the Spirit,</hi> were moſt plentifully poured out upon them, and ſo many of them, as are neceſſary for the <hi>Conduct of the Church,</hi> in all Ages ſince, have accompanied that holy Calling, to that degree, as has been thought ſufficient to denominate them the <hi>Spiritualty,</hi> in diſtinction from the <hi>Temporalty,</hi> in the eſteem of all <hi>Christians:</hi> till the <hi>Papacy</hi> abuſing the <hi>Name,</hi> render'd it leſs grateful to the ears of thoſe, who ſhook off that <hi>Yoke</hi> in the <hi>Reformation:</hi> And <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe this very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Text,</hi> or <hi>Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſo requiſite to the <hi>reſtoring diſlocated Members,</hi> is but once more uſed in the whole New Teſt. and there joyned with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Correcttion,</hi> as attributed to the <hi>Apostle,</hi> in his managery of the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church, 1 Cor. 4. 21. and <hi>lastly,</hi> becauſe we find the word <hi>Spiritual,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to thoſe <hi>extraordinary Perſons</hi> in the Church, which were called <hi>Prophets,</hi> and made uſe of, as equivalent, in common uſe, thereto; as in the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 37. in the <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>Duty,</hi> all that are in any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Station,</hi> are (according to the <hi>Truſt</hi> Repoſed in them,) to mind, in reference to all committed to your <hi>Inſpection:</hi> and, are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly engaged thereunto, in this <hi>Church of England</hi> at their <hi>Ordination:</hi> they are to <hi>preach the Word; to be instant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon; to reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering, and doctrine.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 2. and by the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>Communion,</hi> are allowed to exerciſe ſome <hi>Power of Diſcipline,</hi> with due deference to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in caſe of <hi>ſcandalous Offenders.</hi> And indeed, hereof we are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46829:8"/> ſure, that the chief Power of <hi>Church-diſcipline,</hi> as it was at firſt committed to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Men; and by them derived by <hi>Ordination</hi> to the ſucceſſive <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the Churches Planted by them: ſo it hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, till of late Years, been exerciſed by <hi>Biſhops:</hi> (the whole Current of <hi>Antiquity</hi> giving us abundant Proofs hereof, as to Matter of Fact,) who in <hi>many Caſes,</hi> acted therein <hi>alone:</hi> but in the moſt <hi>weighty Matters,</hi> were aſſiſted by, and acted with a <hi>Presbytery.</hi> But of a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> acting <hi>without,</hi> (and much leſs <hi>againſt)</hi> the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> eſpecially in inflicting <hi>Church cenſures:</hi> I think, (except in <hi>Schiſmatical Churches)</hi> the greateſt Aſſertors of <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> can hardly give us one Inſtance. And to thoſe, who are thus intruſted with <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority,</hi> it belongs, <hi>in the Name of Chriſt,</hi> and with <hi>his Power,</hi> (in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> Phraſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.) to <hi>determine</hi> finally, the Caſes of <hi>ſcandalous Offenders,</hi> and by <hi>Church-cenſures</hi> to proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, (either in order to <hi>their Recovery,</hi> in caſe they be <hi>incurable;</hi> or in order to the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> both in its Health and Reputation, in caſe they be apparently <hi>irrecoverable;)</hi> with more or leſs <hi>Severity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is a <hi>ſtronger Obligation</hi> lies upon them, than upon all the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to lay <hi>themſelves</hi> forth to the utmoſt extent of their Ability and Power, in the purſuance of ſo good a Work. To wit, the <hi>Trust</hi> Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them, by <hi>our Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> who (on the account thereof) are concerned to <hi>watch for their Peoples Souls, as they that muſt give an account.</hi> And they are <hi>Paſtors,</hi> (even ſuch as are of the higheſt denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) only under him, the <hi>chief Shepherd, and Biſhop of Souls,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 25. And therefore, to them it belongs, to uſe all means they can, to <hi>ſeek</hi> out, and reduce to the <hi>Fold</hi> all <hi>ſtraying Sheep,</hi> and to <hi>heal the wounded</hi> of that Flock, <hi>over which the Holy Ghoſt has made them Overſeers,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46829:9"/> or <hi>Biſhops;</hi> that having diſcharged their <hi>Duty herein, when</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Act. 20. 28. 1 Pet. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, they may receive a Crown of Glory.</hi> And if they be <hi>negligent</hi> therein, and the <hi>Sheep periſh</hi> through their <hi>Default;</hi> there is a ſad Doom pronounced in the <hi>Prophet</hi> Ezek. 34. 4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> very applicable to them.</p>
            <p>To which <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Truſt,</hi> there is alſo, (in reference to their particular Charges) another of <hi>Relation.</hi> For the <hi>Pastors,</hi> in ſuch a Caſe, are <hi>Fathers</hi> to their <hi>People,</hi> and they reciprocally, to them their <hi>Children,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 14. <hi>Gal. 4. 19. 1 John 2. 2. 4. 4.</hi> &amp;c. and therefore are they obliged to ſuch <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> towards them, as obligeth them to take care of them, when <hi>ſick, or wounded,</hi> as <hi>Fathers</hi> are wont to do towards their <hi>natural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I ſhewn you, who thoſe <hi>ſpiritual Ones</hi> are, to whom it belongs to <hi>reſtore fallen,</hi> and <hi>wounded Brethren:</hi> and withal told you, that they are not all to perform it in the ſame <hi>Methods:</hi> but each ſort of them, as their <hi>ſtation</hi> in the <hi>Myſtical Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> capacitates them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>And indeed, it is ſo in the <hi>natural Body</hi> alſo, according to which the <hi>Apostle</hi> modules the Regulation of the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Body,</hi> in the chapter before quoted, <hi>1 Cor. 12. 27.</hi> wherein he tells us, that in <hi>both,</hi> there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> (as we read it) <hi>in particular,</hi> i. e. each aſſigned to its <hi>particular Office:</hi> and yet, in thoſe <hi>distingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed Stations,</hi> and <hi>Offices,</hi> they <hi>have,</hi> or ought to <hi>have the ſame Care one for another,</hi> (v. 25.) i. e. alike, and joyntly, to aſſiſt for the good each of other. And as (to apply it to the preſent Caſe) if the leaſt <hi>Toe,</hi> in (the <hi>loweſt</hi> part) the <hi>Foot,</hi> be <hi>wounded,</hi> or <hi>pained</hi> in any kind, every other <hi>Member</hi> is concerned to aſſiſt the Cure: the <hi>ſound Leg</hi> offers it ſelf to ſupport the <hi>wounded</hi> one, <hi>lifted up</hi> by its concurrent Motions, and <hi>laid</hi> on it, that it may in the <hi>eaſieſt posture</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46829:9"/> be preſented to the <hi>Eye,</hi> and <hi>Hand,</hi> to view in what State it is, and apply proper Remedies thereunto; and the very <hi>Head, Shoulders, Neck, Back,</hi> and <hi>Bulk</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> contract themſelves into a narrower Compaſs to facilitate the <hi>Cure:</hi> ſo ſhould it be in the <hi>mystical Body of Christ:</hi> every other <hi>Member,</hi> in its proper place, ought to do what belongs thereto; to aſſiſt the <hi>Restitution</hi> of the <hi>Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> one to its <hi>proper Soundneſs,</hi> and thereby reſtore the whole <hi>Body</hi> to its due State of <hi>Integrity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly, (1) thoſe of the <hi>Spiritualty,</hi> in the <hi>lowest</hi> Notion (according to our former Partition,) even the <hi>meanest Members</hi> of this <hi>ſpiritual Body,</hi> are, as (by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> mutual <hi>Dealing, Acquaintance,</hi> and freedom of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> they have Opportunities offered them,) to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is amiſs in each other, and by ſeaſonable <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions,</hi> and <hi>Reproofs,</hi> to endeavour the <hi>Reformation</hi> thereof, in a <hi>private</hi> Way; and when that will not do, to <hi>acquaint</hi> others, whom the <hi>Offenders</hi> are more likely to be influenced by, of their <hi>Miſdemeanours;</hi> and, as they ſee theſe Endeavours diſappointed by obſtinate <hi>Incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs,</hi> and Crimes grow more <hi>Scandalous</hi> and <hi>Infectious;</hi> to ſhew their diſlike of them, by leſſening their <hi>Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and <hi>Familiarities</hi> of <hi>Converſation</hi> with them: and (laſt of all,) to apply themſelves to the <hi>Officers</hi> of the particular Society of Chriſtians to whom they belong, that they may, in their particular Places, and Subordinations, uſe their Power to <hi>Reclaim,</hi> and <hi>Reform</hi> them.</p>
            <p>(2.) And thoſe <hi>ſpiritual Ones</hi> (in the <hi>ſecond Notion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned,) who are or are eſteemed to be, beyond the Community of Chriſtians, in <hi>Parts,</hi> and <hi>Gifts,</hi> or by <hi>Educaion, Quality,</hi> or <hi>Degree,</hi> capable of doing more Good by their Influence than others; are to take all occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Advantages, which Providence offers them, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among their <hi>Equals,</hi> and thoſe who have any more then ordinary <hi>Deference</hi> for them, or <hi>Dependance</hi> upon them,)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46829:10"/> to ſhame, and put out of <hi>Countenance,</hi> bold and daring <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety,</hi> or <hi>Immorality:</hi> and eſpecially, if, (to all other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages before-mentioned,) they have any part of legal <hi>Authority Annexed,</hi> to employ that, as far as it will extend to thoſe holy Ends; and withal, rendring their Endeavours in that Kind, more Efficacious, by their own <hi>exemplary Piety</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> by Countenancing, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging thoſe in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority,</hi> to the utmoſt of their Power, to the doing of their Duty, that by their joynt Concurrence, the <hi>greateſt Offenders</hi> may, (as well as the <hi>meaneſt)</hi> be brought under thoſe due <hi>Methods</hi> of <hi>Cure,</hi> in reference to their ſpiritual Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>(3) And <hi>laſtly,</hi> thoſe who by <hi>Office</hi> in the Church, are (as I before told you) moſt peculiarly Entituled to the Denomination of <hi>ſpiritual Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> are, (when all other Means have been uſed, and prove <hi>inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual,)</hi> to put the laſt Hand, to this Holy and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Work, in their <hi>Church-judicatories:</hi> to <hi>call Criminals</hi> before them, when they come to their Notice by regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Information,</hi> and <hi>Preſentment;</hi> or otherwiſe, to <hi>examine</hi> their <hi>Facts</hi> with their particular aggravating, or leſſening Circumſtances: and upon full Examination, Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to Admoniſh and Exhort, and Reprove them, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to paſs <hi>Judgment,</hi> and by the <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to <hi>Proſecute</hi> them, either to <hi>their Amendment,</hi> by enjoyning them ſuch <hi>penitential</hi> Acknowledgments of their <hi>Crimes,</hi> as may teſtifie their <hi>Repentance</hi> for them, ſatisfie the Church for the <hi>Scandal</hi> given by them, and (by the <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> which they have occaſioned them to undergo,) both <hi>preſerve themſelves</hi> from <hi>relapſing</hi> into the ſame, or like Sins, and <hi>others</hi> by their Examples, from ſuch <hi>Courſes:</hi> and if they ſhall obſtinately refuſe ſuch a Saluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferus <hi>Penance,</hi> to proceed to the <hi>greater,</hi> or leſſer <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> as the Degrees of their Obſtinacy deſerve. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> upon their returning to a better Mind, (in caſe thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46829:10"/> 
               <hi>Methods,</hi> through God's Grace, reduce them,) to grant them <hi>Abſolution</hi> in the Name of <hi>Christ,</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> and thereby, to <hi>looſen</hi> thoſe they have <hi>bound,</hi> to <hi>forgive them, reſtore</hi> them to the <hi>Communion</hi> of the Church, and <hi>confirm their Love</hi> to them, in the Senſe of thoſe <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Expreſſions,</hi> uſed to that purpoſe, <hi>Matth. 16, 19. 18, 18. John 20. 23. 2 Cor. 2. 7, 8.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And thus having ſhewed you all, how far you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, in, and by what <hi>Means,</hi> and <hi>Methods,</hi> you, and all others are to perform your and their Parts, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ſo <hi>Chriſtian a Duty;</hi> I think, the moſt proper <hi>uſe</hi> of all this Diſcourſe that we can make, is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>reflect</hi> with holy <hi>Grief,</hi> upon the great <hi>Defects</hi> in point of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline;</hi> ordained by our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> for ſo Great and Holy an End, which at this Day, all <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> lie under, and the great <hi>Danger</hi> of ſo many Souls in them, for want of <hi>ſufficient Remedies</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſtempers</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> they are <hi>expoſed</hi> to, and too often <hi>over-run</hi> withal. There being hardly any Church in the World, that ſince the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of <hi>Miracles,</hi> (which kept the World in Awe by the Atteſtation they gave of the <hi>divine Authority,</hi> backing the <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> with! <hi>dreadful Executions</hi> of <hi>obſtinate Offenders)</hi> ever attained to that <hi>intrinſick Power,</hi> as to be able to ſtand on its <hi>own Legs;</hi> but has been fain to call in the <hi>Civil Magiſtracy</hi> to its Aſſiſtance: (and in moſt places) has too unhappily purchaſed its Aſſiſtance, with the conſiderable leſſening of its Orthodoxy, Unity, or Revenues; and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of its <hi>original Authority,</hi> to accommodate the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts</hi> of particular <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Earneſtly to <hi>deſire</hi> (as <hi>our Church</hi> Profeſſeth to do) <hi>that the godly Diſcipline of the Primitive Church, of putting all who are Convicted of notorious Sin, to open Penance, were in its original Perfection reſtored again,</hi> in order to the great Ends there mentioned: <hi>that the</hi> Criminals <hi>being</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46829:11"/> 
               <hi>Puniſhed in this World, their Souls may be ſaved in the Day of the Lord; and that others Admoniſhed by their Example, may be the more afraid to offend.</hi> And ſuch <hi>Deſires,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in our <hi>earneſt Prayers</hi> to God, it may be hoped, may induce him, in time, to make <hi>all the Kingdoms of the Earth (in this reſpect) the Kingdoms of the Lord, and his Chriſt,</hi> according to that <hi>prophetical Promiſe,</hi> Apoc. 11. 15. the <hi>means</hi> of fulfilling whereof, and the <hi>Times and Seaſons</hi> wherein it is to be Accompliſhed, have filled the Chriſtian World with ſo many <hi>Diſputes,</hi> from the Times of the firſt <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> down to our Dayes; and ſo many irregular <hi>Attempts</hi> of <hi>Indiſcreet,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>furious Zeal</hi> to Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh it. and we have another comfortable <hi>Promiſe,</hi> applicable to that purpoſe; that, when the <hi>Lords Time ſhall come to build up his</hi> Zion, <hi>he will appear in his Glory, and not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe, but regard the Prayer of his deſtitute Church,</hi> &amp;c. Pſ. 102. 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And to the utmoſt of our Power, to <hi>preſerve,</hi> and keep in <hi>exerciſe</hi> ſo much of it, in the mean time, as <hi>yet remains</hi> to us, in this <hi>general Decay;</hi> which though (through the <hi>Indulgenoe</hi> of our <hi>Laws,</hi> it reach not all Offendors; yet) is ſufficiently aſſiſted by them, to <hi>redreſs,</hi> if well follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, moſt <hi>notorious Immoral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties;</hi> or at leaſt, to render them ſo <hi>uneaſie</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>guilty</hi> of them; that 'tis much <hi>our Fault,</hi> that they dare appear ſo <hi>Open-faced</hi> in the ſight of the Sun, as they daily do. So that, (in this Caſe, at leaſt,) it muſt needs be highly unreaſonable, for the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from our <hi>Church,</hi> to impute the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch <hi>Crimes</hi> to the <hi>Church-conſtitution;</hi> and from thence to frame <hi>colourable Excuſes</hi> for their <hi>Separations</hi> from it; when <hi>they themſelves,</hi> would they joyn with us ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, for the Proſecution of them, might ſoon remove that <hi>Scandal</hi> out of the way; which I am afraid, (whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they pretend) too many of them are ſecretly willing ſhould continue there, for the carrying on of thoſe <hi>By-ends</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46829:11"/> of their own, to which they find the <hi>Prejudices</hi> thence raiſed ſo Serviceable.</p>
            <p>But (to ſhut up this Head) if we cannot herein get their <hi>hearty Aſſiſtances,</hi> who ſtand <hi>divided</hi> from us; let thoſe of us, at leaſt, who profeſs to own <hi>parochial Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> (and eſpecially the <hi>Officers</hi> of theſe <hi>Churches</hi> legally <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 23.</note> Conſtituted,) rather chooſe (with <hi>Moſes)</hi> to <hi>ſtand alone in the Gap,</hi> then endanger the breaking in of God's Wrath upon us, for ſuffering our <hi>Laws,</hi> ſo ſar as they will extend, to ſleep, in ſo general an <hi>Inundation</hi> of <hi>licentious Debauchery:</hi> Let us, (after private <hi>Admonitions</hi> and <hi>Reproofs,</hi> tryed in vain, <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5 14.</note> by <hi>warning the Unruly,)</hi> make <hi>ſaithful Preſentments</hi> of <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible Offenders</hi> to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judicatories;</hi> that they may either be <hi>Reſtored</hi> to a ſounder <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and better <hi>Converſation,</hi> by <hi>publick Penance,</hi> or the Church rid of them, (both as to Infection, and Scandal) by <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And thus much ſhall ſuffice, to be ſpoken of the <hi>Duty</hi> here enjoyned; and the <hi>Perſons</hi> who are to <hi>perform</hi> it; and what their <hi>ſeveral Parts</hi> are, wherein they muſt contribute to ſo good a Work: So that there now reſts only (on this Head) the <hi>Manner</hi> how they are each of them to diſcharge it, to be conſidered: and that is <hi>(in the Spirit of Meekneſs.)</hi> as follows in the <hi>Text, (he that is overtaken in a fault, muſt be reſtored,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>in a meek manner, by thoſe that undertake the Cure.</hi> For the Explication of which <hi>Phraſe,</hi> you muſt know, 1 <hi>That.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Vertue</hi> here recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and rendred, <hi>Meekneſs;</hi> is, (as <hi>Moraliſts</hi> define it,) a <hi>Vertue, which Checks, and keeps within due Bounds of Modcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the otherwiſe unruly Paſſions of Anger and Revenge; and renders thoſe Wild-beaſt like Emotions of Mans Soul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>tame;</hi> which is the proper Notion of the <hi>Greek Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2ly.</hi> That this <hi>moral Vertue,</hi> as it is improved by <hi>divine Grace,</hi> becomes a <hi>Fruit of the Holy Spirit,</hi> and is mentioned as ſuch, by our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the <hi>Chap.</hi> next preceeding this, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 23. v. 23. And hence, <hi>Interpreters</hi> ordinarily are apt to derive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46829:12"/> the reaſon of this annexing <hi>(Spirit)</hi> to <hi>(Meekneſs)</hi> in the <hi>Text;</hi> ſo, that the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> in this Notion, means only ſuch a <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> as is the <hi>Fruit of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I think rather, the reaſon of joyning <hi>(Spirit)</hi> to <hi>(Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs)</hi> here, is rather to be ſetched from <hi>parallel Phraſes,</hi> in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and ſo is an <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> as many other Forms of Speaking are, in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> Now the <hi>Hebrews frequently</hi> uſe, to expreſs any <hi>vehement Impulſe,</hi> or <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>frequent Propenſion</hi> of the Mind, to ſuch or ſuch a thing, by the Name of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> thereof. Thus (in <hi>evil things)</hi> is the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Jealouſie,</hi> uſed for a <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>vehement Jealouſie,</hi> Num. 5. 14. <hi>A Spirit of Whoredomes,</hi> for a <hi>vehement Inclination</hi> to <hi>whoredomes.</hi> Hoſ. 4. 12. A <hi>Spirit of deep ſleep,</hi> for a <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual lethargical Propenſion.</hi> Iſ. 29. 10. and (in <hi>good things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo)</hi> a <hi>Spirit of Underſtanding,</hi> Job 20. 3. <hi>and Judgment,</hi> Iſ. 4. 4. and <hi>Counſel, and the Fear of the Lord,</hi> Iſ. 11. 3. (not excluding the <hi>Original</hi> of them, as deriving themſelves from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,) cannote,</hi> the <hi>Powerful,</hi> and <hi>plentiful</hi> Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> then in the <hi>Text,</hi> (according to this Notion,) denotes a <hi>ſtrong Inclination</hi> to, and a large <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> upon ſuch Occaſions, exerciſed towards <hi>fallen Brethren,</hi> for your <hi>Reſtitution, poſſeſſing,</hi> and ſtrongly <hi>influencing</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> of thoſe who go about ſo Charitable a Work; which by <hi>paſſionate Applications,</hi> would be <hi>retarded,</hi> as a <hi>Wound</hi> in the <hi>Body,</hi> by too <hi>rigid Handling,</hi> is oftentimes the longer e'er it be <hi>Cured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> whereof is here recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, is not to be underſtood in a <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rict philoſophical Senſe,</hi> as it is confined to the <hi>Regulation</hi> of the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of <hi>Anger</hi> and <hi>Revenge</hi> only; but in a <hi>larger Notion,</hi> as it lays Reſtraints al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo on thoſe of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Contempt of others:</hi> And ſo it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in its Compaſs, thoſe excellent <hi>Qualities</hi> that follow, that is, <hi>(firſt)</hi> of <hi>Patience,</hi> in undergoing the greateſt <hi>Evils</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> as owning that we deſerve <hi>worſe;</hi> and <hi>thankfulneſs</hi> for <hi>the leaſt Mercies,</hi> as judging our ſelves unworthy of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46829:12"/> them; (2) <hi>modeſt</hi> Submiſſion to our <hi>Superiours,</hi> among <hi>Men; obeying</hi> their <hi>Lawful,</hi> and <hi>candidly interpreting</hi> their <hi>dubious Commands.</hi> 3 all obliging <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>reſpectful Civilities</hi> to our <hi>Equals;</hi> rather <hi>preferring them in Honour,</hi> then contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them for <hi>Punctilio</hi>'s of that Nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. Eſpecially, if they be <hi>good Men:</hi> it much becoming the <hi>meek Soul, (with</hi> St. <hi>Paul)</hi> to look on himſelf, as <hi>leſs then the leaſt of Saints.</hi> Eph. 3. 8. and if they be <hi>bad,</hi> to <hi>leſſen</hi> their <hi>Crimes,</hi> in ballance with our <hi>own,</hi> and (by his Example) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on our ſelves as <hi>chief of Sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 15. (4) <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>Mildly</hi> and <hi>Prudently</hi> taking notice of their <hi>Faults;</hi> and <hi>taking</hi> it <hi>kindly</hi> from them, when they in like manner <hi>take notice of ours,</hi> and <hi>reprove</hi> us for them; (5) <hi>not rejoycing,</hi> though they be our <hi>Enemies;</hi> in any Ill they <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>ſuffer,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 6, (6) not haſtily <hi>quarelling</hi> them for <hi>little Injuries,</hi> and being ready to <hi>receive,</hi> and give moderate <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> for ſuch, on either ſide.</p>
            <p>7. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> towards <hi>Inferiours,</hi> ſhewing our ſelves <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible,</hi> and <hi>Treatable</hi> to the <hi>Meaneſt</hi> of them: and being ready, on juſt Occaſions, to do them all <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Humanity,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> never oppreſſing them by our <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Purſe;</hi> nor in any Caſe, <hi>Tyrannically</hi> uſing the <hi>Advantages</hi> we have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, or with a contemptuous <hi>Imperiouſneſs, provoking them to Wrath,</hi> Eph. 6. 4. and <hi>moderating Threatnings,</hi> (and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections)</hi> by <hi>What is Juſt and Equal,</hi> v. 9. and <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 1. yea if <hi>Children,</hi> or even <hi>Slaves</hi> to us, (as moſt <hi>Servants</hi> were, when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gave theſe <hi>Directions,</hi> but now mentioned.)</p>
            <p>And by theſe, and the like <hi>Meaſures,</hi> (in the Caſe of an <hi>offending Brothers</hi> Reſtitution) are all to ſhew this <hi>Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Even <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Officers,</hi> that have the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>or rod,</hi> are not to uſe it <hi>always,</hi> nor indeed, ever when <hi>Lenity</hi> will <hi>prevail;</hi> but rather, (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> intimates he deſired, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 21.) to <hi>reclaim Offenders</hi> with <hi>the ſpirit of Meekneſs:</hi> and when their <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> calls for it, to lay on that <hi>Rod</hi> moſt <note place="margin">Jer. 31. 30.</note> ſeveraly, and withal, to ſhew with how much <hi>unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> they are <hi>forced</hi> to it, and that their <hi>fatherly Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:46829:13"/> (as <hi>Gods</hi> towards <hi>Ephraim)</hi> are <hi>troubled for them;</hi> and <hi>pronounce Sentence,</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth againſt the irregular <hi>Walkers</hi> among the <hi>Philippians,</hi> ch. 3. 18, 19.) when he daclar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them <hi>Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> and denounceth the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> from God impendent over them,) with <hi>compaſſionate Tears,</hi> or equivalent Indications of <hi>Condolency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And with a <hi>Spirit</hi> much of the ſame Temper, ſhould all <hi>other Chriſtians</hi> carry themſelves, in the ſeveral Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, wherein their <hi>Brethren's falls</hi> come under their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. If their <hi>Crimes</hi> be only <hi>Private,</hi> their <hi>Admonitions</hi> and <hi>Reproofs</hi> are to be ſo too; and thoſe managed with all <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, Kind,</hi> and <hi>diſcreet Deportment,</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable; and <hi>patiently reiterated</hi> again, and again, with ſuch a <hi>Long-ſuffering</hi> as God uſes towards us, to <hi>bring us to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9.</p>
            <p>And if, at laſt, we are enforced by our Duty to make the <hi>Crimes</hi> more <hi>known,</hi> by calling in the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of others; not to do it <hi>Raſhly,</hi> and in a <hi>Paſſion,</hi> but <hi>Deliberately,</hi> and with that <hi>Gradation</hi> which our <hi>Saviour</hi> commands us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 17. and when it comes in the Iſſue, to the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the Offenders are by juſt <hi>Penance</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to <hi>publick Shame,</hi> we are not to entertain them (in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before us, and the Congregation) with <hi>Countenances,</hi> and <hi>Carriages,</hi> importing <hi>Lightneſs,</hi> and <hi>Frothineſs</hi> of <hi>Spirit</hi> much leſs, with <hi>Jeers, Flouts,</hi> or <hi>Reproaches,</hi> in <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſture:</hi> but with a <hi>Serious</hi> and <hi>compoſed Gravity</hi> of <hi>Spirit;</hi> and <hi>Demeanour</hi> through the <hi>whole Action;</hi> ſuch as may ſpeak <hi>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitiful</hi> and compaſſionate <hi>Spectator</hi> of ſo ſad a <hi>Scene,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> withal <hi>devout Aſſiſtants</hi> of them, and the <hi>Congregation</hi> in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conjoyned <hi>Prayers</hi> for them: and laſtly, when the <hi>Action <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> over,</hi> and they <hi>Authoritatively Reſtored</hi> to the <hi>Peace of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church,</hi> and <hi>Re-admitted</hi> to the <hi>Communion</hi> of that holy Soc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ety; we ought to be ready to <hi>Re-admit</hi> them alſo into ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>particular Affections,</hi> and with all <hi>brotherly Kindneſs</hi> to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brace</hi> them, to <hi>give them the right Hand of Fellowſhip,</hi> to we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46829:13"/> them again into <hi>Chriſts Fold,</hi> from whence they <hi>ſtrayed:</hi> and thence forward no more to remember their <hi>former Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> and much leſs, to <hi>Reproach</hi> them with, and <hi>cast</hi> in their <hi>Teeth</hi> thoſe Crimes, which they have by their <hi>Penitence,</hi> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away. For ſuch a Carriage, in ſuch Caſes, is both <hi>Unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>Unchriſtian. Unmanly,</hi> as that which is <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with <hi>good Breeding,</hi> in the Judgment of all <hi>civil Societies;</hi> and much more <hi>Unchriſtian,</hi> as that which directly breaks one of Chriſt's <hi>great Commands</hi> of <hi>mutual Forgiveneſs,</hi> Eph. 4. 32. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12, 13. and upon the <hi>Non-performance</hi> whereof, our very <hi>Pardon</hi> from God himſelf, is <hi>Suſpended. Matt.</hi> 6. 14. Mark 11. 25, 26. Nay more, our very <hi>Prayers</hi> are denied <hi>Acceſs</hi> to him for <hi>Pardon</hi> to our ſelves; we not being warranted to <hi>ask</hi> it, but on that Condition. <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. 12. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Command,</hi> as does, not only enjoyn the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> but alſo ſets us the juſt <hi>Meaſure</hi> of Performance, even the <hi>Example</hi> of our <hi>Heavenly Father.</hi> and our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4. 32. before quoted. Wherein we are enjoyned to <hi>forgive, as God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven us:</hi> And how that is, the Scripture in many <hi>emphatical Forms</hi> of Speech tells us: To wit, by <hi>blotting out our Tranſgreſſions,</hi> and <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring our Sins.</hi> Iſ. 43. 25. <hi>Forgiving our Iniquity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring our ſin no more.</hi> Jer. 31. 34. <hi>And caſting all our ſins into the depths of the ſea.</hi> Mic. 7. 19. <hi>And behind his back, (ſo, as never to look on them any more.)</hi> Iſ. 38. 17. Yea ſo, as (ſuppoſing they ſhould be ſought for) thenceforward, <hi>never to be found.</hi> Jer. 50. 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, in effect, he that <hi>Reproacheth</hi> his <hi>Brother</hi> in this Caſe, does indeed <hi>curſe himſelf,</hi> when he <hi>prays</hi> God <hi>to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, as he forgives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>III. And thus I have diſpatched the <hi>main Thing,</hi> I intended on this Occaſion to Proſecute; to wit, (the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Reſtoring our fallen Brethren with the Spirit of Meekneſs.)</hi> I have only remaining, to touch in a few Words, the <hi>two Motives</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here urgeth, to induce us to perform it in the manner Preſcribed: after which, (with a few Words relating to the Occaſion) I ſhall conclude. Which <hi>Motives,</hi> (as I told you before,) are <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46829:14"/>1. The <hi>conſideration</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> as liable to the ſame <hi>Tenptations,</hi> by which <hi>others</hi> are <hi>overtaken.</hi> And this, as we are <hi>Men,</hi> ought to prevail with us, to <hi>conſider</hi> our <hi>fallen Brethren,</hi> as thoſe betwixt whom and us, only the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> (not any <hi>Prerogative,</hi> or <hi>peculiar Power,</hi> or Vertue of our <hi>own)</hi> hath put a <hi>Difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Which <hi>Motive</hi> it concerns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> even the <hi>moſt Spiritual,</hi> ſuch as are moſt eminently ſo, by <hi>Office</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> and though (as I before intimated) it ought not to induce them to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Rod</hi> of Correction altogether, where the Caſe requires it; yet ought to prevail even with <hi>them,</hi> not to uſe it, where it may without <hi>hazard</hi> of <hi>Souls,</hi> and <hi>Scandal</hi> to the Church, be <hi>forborn:</hi> and when Neceſſity inforceth them to uſe it, to ſhew, as I told you before, by their <hi>Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery</hi> thereof, that their <hi>Duty,</hi> not their <hi>Inclination</hi> puts them upon it. For even they are obliged, (by the ſad <hi>Examples,</hi> both in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and too common <hi>Experience</hi> ſet before them) to <hi>conſider themſelves,</hi> as <hi>liable to be Tempted,</hi> either with the <hi>ſame,</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> as <hi>foul Crimes</hi> as thoſe are, which they are to <hi>Cenſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And the like uſe ought every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in the Church to make of this <hi>Motive,</hi> who either is, or thinks himſelf <hi>more Spiritual,</hi> then <hi>others,</hi> whoſe Actions ſpeak them (in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Phraſe)</hi> more <hi>Carnal.</hi> For to every ſuch Perſon, in a particular <hi>Apostrophe,</hi> my <hi>Text</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>(conſider thy ſelf, leaſt thou alſo be tempted.)</hi> Noah, and <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and man other great <hi>Saints</hi> in Scripture, are for this end ſet before the beſt of us, as Examples <hi>for our Admonition;</hi> leſt, when we <hi>think our ſelves to ſtand</hi> moſt ſecure, we be in like manner <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered to fall.</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And moſt of all are thoſe concerned, to lay this <hi>Motive</hi> to Heart, who, when any of their Brethren are expoſed to <hi>Shame</hi> as <hi>Criminals,</hi> are moſt apt to vent their <hi>Spleen</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words them, in an unſavory <hi>inſulting</hi> Way; and withal, to <hi>flatter themſelves in their own Eyes,</hi> and <hi>Vaunt</hi> themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>others,</hi> (though they be <hi>Carnal</hi> enough as to other <hi>Fruits</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46829:14"/> 
               <hi>of the Fleſh)</hi> that they are not ſuch <hi>Sinners,</hi> as thoſe whom (with the <hi>Publican,</hi> Luke 18. 13.) they ſee <hi>beating their Breaſts,</hi> and begging <hi>Mercy</hi> of God, and the Congregation to which yet, would they <hi>conſider themſelves,</hi> as our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, might eaſily find, that though they are not open <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers,</hi> or <hi>Fornicators,</hi> yet poſſibly they are, <hi>ſecretly ſuch,</hi> or (if not ſo, neither yet) <hi>common Swearers,</hi> or <hi>Drunkards,</hi> or profane <hi>Scoffers</hi> at <hi>Religion:</hi> or, if they make a ſhew of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>Piety</hi> before the <hi>World,</hi> yet) poſſibly <hi>cheating Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Exactors, Oppreſſors, Grinders of the Faces of the Poor; Hereticks,</hi> or <hi>ſchiſmatical Dividers of the Church;</hi> and becauſe of thoſe <hi>Vices,</hi> deſerve a <hi>place</hi> among thoſe <hi>Penitents,</hi> whom they <hi>Inſult</hi> over; and may one Day wiſh they had taken part of their <hi>Penance</hi> with them, rather than after, <hi>being highly eſteemed in the Eyes of Men;</hi> to be eternally <hi>an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Luke 16. 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecend Motive</hi> here tendred to our Conſideration, is, that by treating <hi>offending Brethren,</hi> in order to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery with the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> (and ſo <hi>bearing their Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> by a compaſſionate Temper towards them,) we Act as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and <hi>(fulfil the Law of Chriſt;)</hi> who hath herein placed a great part of that <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> which his Religion Conducts us to. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 5. Hath <hi>commended</hi> it to us by his <hi>own Example;</hi> and made this a part of that <hi>eaſie Yoke,</hi> which he lays on us, in order to our everlaſting <hi>Reſt,</hi> to <hi>learn of him to be meek and lowly in heart,</hi> Matt. 11. 28, 29, 30. And indeed, there is nothing, wherein his <hi>Life</hi> was more eminently <hi>Exemplary,</hi> than in his <hi>Meekneſs</hi> towards <hi>penitent Offenders.</hi> And we may make a gueſs at his <hi>Temper</hi> toward ſuch, by his frequent <hi>Converſation,</hi> (in order to the <hi>Reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> them,) with <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> in oppoſition to the ſowre Humor of the auſtere <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Matt. 9. 11, 12, 13. 11. 19. By his <hi>Treatment</hi> of the <hi>Woman,</hi> that Penitently <hi>waſhed his feet with tears,</hi> and <hi>wiped them with the hairs of her head, &amp;c.</hi> Luke 7. 38, 39. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>the other Woman</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of <hi>Adultery,</hi> John 8. 10, 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who, though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46829:15"/> there be no peculiar Acts of her <hi>Penitence</hi> expreſſed; yet, it muſt be ſuppoſed, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaw that in her, which rendred her malleable to receive the <hi>Impreſſions</hi> of that <hi>meek Diſmiſſion</hi> from him, with Aſſurance of his Pardon, provided <hi>ſhe Sinned no more;</hi> i. e. left her Lewd Courſe of Life every way, and particularly preſerved her <hi>Chaſtity</hi> Inviolate for the future.</p>
            <p>If then, there be ſo much of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in this <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here recommends to us: the <hi>contrary Temper</hi> muſt neceſſarily, be <hi>Unchriſtian,</hi> as well as <hi>Inhumane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I at length, diſpatched the <hi>words,</hi> as they relate to the <hi>Duty</hi> of thoſe who are <hi>not Criminal,</hi> toward ſuch as <hi>are</hi> ſo: to wit, the <hi>Reſtoring</hi> them <hi>with the Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> But I muſt not, in the cloſe of this Diſcourſe, omit to touch ſomewhat on the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Criminals</hi> themſelves towards thoſe who <hi>endeavour</hi> to <hi>reſtore</hi> them. For the <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>one ſort,</hi> will rationally follow from that of the other; both as to the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf to be done, and the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>thing to be done,</hi> if the <hi>ſpiritual Brethren</hi> be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to <hi>reſtore</hi> the <hi>fallen Ones,</hi> it is moſt highly reaſonable, that they themſelves ſhould not be <hi>unwilling,</hi> but rather rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily <hi>comply</hi> with their Endeavours, in order to their <hi>own Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</hi> For indeed, <hi>Self-love,</hi> is the <hi>meaſure</hi> by which all <hi>Love</hi> to our <hi>Neighbours</hi> is to be regulated.</p>
            <p>And proportionably, here, <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>himſelf</hi> in the <hi>wounded Pationt,</hi> (in reaſon,) ought to Operate more ſtrongly on him to <hi>deſire</hi> to be <hi>Cured;</hi> than <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> or <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> can Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon the <hi>Chyrurgeon,</hi> to be at the <hi>Pains,</hi> or <hi>Charge</hi> to <hi>Cure</hi> him. And therefore, when any ones <hi>Conſcience Smites</hi> him for the moſt <hi>ſecret Sins,</hi> and he cannot by his own En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours betwixt God and his own <hi>Soul,</hi> recover his <hi>inward Peace;</hi> it is certainly, his Duty, of himſelf, to <hi>open</hi> his <hi>Wound</hi> to ſome skilful <hi>ſpiritual Chirurgeon,</hi> and commit himſelf Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily to his <hi>Conduct</hi> for his <hi>Cure;</hi> and eſpecially, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other, to his own <hi>Paſtor,</hi> who is <hi>over him in the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 12, 14.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46829:15"/>
            <p>And if Men's <hi>Sins</hi> be <hi>known</hi> to <hi>others;</hi> they are not to think <hi>themſelves Affronted,</hi> if they be <hi>reproved</hi> by any of them; much leſs, muſt they <hi>quarrel</hi> them, for not being willing to <hi>ſuffer Sin upon them;</hi> but rather take it as <hi>a Kindneſs,</hi> that the <hi>righteous ſmites them,</hi> Pſal. 141. 5.</p>
            <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi> if the Sin be <hi>Publickly,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalouſly Notorious;</hi> they ſhould be ready to uſe all lawful <hi>Means,</hi> yea, rather, ſeek out after <hi>the</hi> moſt <hi>proper Expedients,</hi> in order to the giving as <hi>publick Satisfaction</hi> to the <hi>offended Congregation;</hi> and much more, are they obliged to comply with the <hi>lawful Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſubmit to the <hi>Methods,</hi> which in this Caſe are appointed for their <hi>Reſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For otherwiſe, they will incur the deſperate <hi>Hazard</hi> of <hi>hardening their Hearts,</hi> and <hi>Necks</hi> in <hi>Sin</hi> and endanger them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>judicially hardned</hi> by God, till they be <hi>Deſtroyed without Remedy;</hi> according to the dreadful Threatnings, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled againſt ſuch <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> in Scripture, eſpecially, <hi>Pſal. 95. 8. Heb. 3. 15.</hi> and <hi>Pſal. 81. 12. Prov. 28. 14, 29. 1 John 12. 40. Rom. 2. 5. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And as to the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it; there is <hi>as much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> why the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs</hi> ſhould ſhew it ſelf in the <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Brethren</hi> as in thoſe, who undertake to <hi>Reſtore them.</hi> Yea, indeed, much more; becauſe (as in the <hi>Body,</hi> ſo in the <hi>Soul,)</hi> any <hi>diſorderly Paſſion,</hi> is apt to <hi>Inflame</hi> a <hi>Wound,</hi> and render the <hi>Cure</hi> more <hi>Tedious,</hi> and <hi>Hazardous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, in their Caſe, they have no appearance of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to juſtifie them in the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of <hi>Anger,</hi> or <hi>Revenge.</hi> For who can think it Rational, to be <hi>angry</hi> with another, for ſuch <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> as really, and in due Eſtimation, carry in them the greateſt, and moſt obliging <hi>Kindneſſes;</hi> and ſuch are indeed, all <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>charitable Attempts,</hi> to <hi>Reſcue</hi> a Man from <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> the greateſt Evils, yea, though the <hi>Attempter,</hi> (through <hi>Haſte,</hi> and <hi>inconſiderate Zeal,</hi> ſhould be undecently <hi>rough,</hi> and forget his wonted <hi>Meekneſs;</hi> yet his <hi>Love,</hi> in ſuch a Caſe, in all reaſon, ſhould excuſe his <hi>Rudeneſs.</hi> And afterwards, to <hi>reflect</hi> on this, as deſerving a <hi>Revenge;</hi> is certainly, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46829:16"/> as it is to return <hi>Evil</hi> for <hi>Good,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of, asa moſt unaccountable Malice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. 4, 5, And as little colour of <hi>Reaſon</hi> can ſuch Perſons have for <hi>Pride,</hi> which another way is wont to diſlodge <hi>Meekneſs.</hi> For there is nothing more unreaſonable, then for a <hi>deformed Perſon,</hi> to be lifted up with Opinion of his own <hi>Beauty;</hi> and all Sin is a <hi>Deformity</hi> to the <hi>Soul.</hi> For him, then, that is notoriouſly <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal,</hi> to be <hi>Proud,</hi> and <hi>Impatient</hi> to be looked on, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as he deſerves; is ſo very unbecoming, that it ordinarily gives the greateſt Tentation to others, to break the <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> towards him, and turns their <hi>Pity</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi> into <hi>Scorn</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> in the <hi>higheſt Degree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the <hi>Duty,</hi> I am, (in the laſt place,) to preſs upon you, that now appear as <hi>Penitents,</hi> in this <hi>Congregation.</hi> It is certainly, to be commended in you, that you have been <hi>willing</hi> to <hi>accept of the Puniſhment,</hi> the <hi>Church in Chriſt's Name,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lev. 26. 41.</note> hath inflicted on you for your <hi>Iniquity.</hi> And I hope, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from an <hi>hearty deſire</hi> to be <hi>reſtored</hi> to your <hi>Integrity,</hi> by <hi>Repentance;</hi> and that the <hi>Confeſſions</hi> you are to make before God and his Church, will be accompanied with a <hi>deep ſenſe of true Sorrow,</hi> and <hi>brokenneſs of Heart,</hi> which may render it <hi>as acceptable a ſacrifice to God,</hi> as <hi>David's</hi> was, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 17. and that none of you will play the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> with God, and his Church, in profeſſing that <hi>outwardly,</hi> which <hi>inwardly</hi> you do not feel. And indeed, according to your <hi>Sincerity</hi> herein, you are to expect <hi>God's Pardon;</hi> and according to the <hi>Evidence</hi> you give thereof, by your <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>humble Demeanour,</hi> (joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the other <hi>circumſtantial Evidences</hi> of <hi>true Sorrow,</hi> which naturally attend it where it is ſo) you will be entitled to the <hi>Churches</hi> alſo. And I muſt tell you, the <hi>Church</hi> will have the more reaſon to be ſatisfied herein, by your <hi>meek Submiſſion</hi> to thoſe <hi>Habits,</hi> and <hi>Rites</hi> of <hi>Penitence,</hi> which ſhe, in Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the ancient Times, enjoyns you, of all which, (and they were very many) our <hi>Church,</hi> (becauſe many of the reſt were abuſed by the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church, when they thought fit to make <hi>Penance</hi> a <hi>Sacrament,)</hi> has thought fit generally to retain but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46829:16"/> 
               <hi>two:</hi> that of the <hi>white Sheet,</hi> and <hi>Wand,</hi> with which her <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> are enjoyned (if the <hi>Crimes</hi> require it,) to appear, and where they do not, ſhe hath liberty, even to diſpenſe with them.</p>
            <p>That of the <hi>Sheet,</hi> is only <hi>enjoyned</hi> to you—; all the reſt being admitted, only in their <hi>Courſe working-day apparrel,</hi> with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Wand,</hi> to acknowledge they juſtly deſerved the <hi>Zod</hi> of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> ſhould be uſed towards them. And the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of that <hi>Difference,</hi> is; (as I ſuppoſe) becauſe your <hi>Offence</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to your <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judges,</hi> accompanied with many groſs and foul Circumſtances of <hi>wanton Dalliance,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Wife</hi> of <hi>another Man,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> alſo, a <hi>married Perſon,</hi> gave a <hi>ſcandalous Appearance,</hi> and <hi>notorious</hi> cauſe of <hi>Suſpicion</hi> of <hi>actual Adultery;</hi> from which Suſpicion the <hi>Defences</hi> you made, did not, (in their Judgment) ſufficiently <hi>clear</hi> you;) as you <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> enjoyns you to acknowledge: whereas, the <hi>Crime</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, was of an <hi>inferiour Guilt,</hi> though very <hi>great</hi> too, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Aggravation of it, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 13. &amp;c.) and they humbly <hi>offered</hi> themſelves to their <hi>Penance,</hi> before the <hi>Court</hi> had <hi>paſſed Judgment</hi> upon them, in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>But, if they had required you <hi>all,</hi> to have <hi>appeared</hi> in the like <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>innen Garb;</hi> I know no reaſon, why <hi>any</hi> of you ſhould have <hi>waved</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, on that Account. A <hi>courſe ſquare Sheet,</hi> without being <hi>Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,</hi> or <hi>Trimmed,</hi> being much of <hi>Kin</hi> to the <hi>Sack-cloath,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntiently <hi>Penitents,</hi> (whom God himſelf in a particular Caſe, required to preſent themſelves before him, <hi>without Ornaments,</hi> Exod. 33. 4, 5, 6.) appeared in, as many <hi>Scriptures</hi> witneſs: only, with this difference, that the <hi>old Sack-cloath</hi> was far <hi>rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and more <hi>pungent,</hi> as being made of <hi>Hair,</hi> not <hi>Flax,</hi> or <hi>Hemp,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ours is. This Imitation however, the Church thought fit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etain, rather than to leave <hi>Penitents,</hi> the choice of <hi>coloured,</hi> and <hi>faſhionable Garments,</hi> leaſt even <hi>Penance</hi> it ſelf, ſhould in time turn to an <hi>Oſtentation</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> in <hi>Apparel,</hi> through the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected <hi>Emulation</hi> of Perſons, vainly inclined to <hi>Singularity</hi> in the <hi>Garb</hi> they Publickly <hi>appear</hi> in.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> in particular, of the Veſt, I am apt to believe, it might owe it ſelf, to the Conformity, which the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46829:17"/> Deſign of <hi>publick Penitence,</hi> bears to that of <hi>Baptiſm. This</hi> being (as the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> call it) the <hi>Baptiſm of Repentance for the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of Sins,</hi> Mark 1. 4. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 3. and <hi>that,</hi> a Profeſſion of <hi>Repentance,</hi> in order to the ſame end, the <hi>reſtoring Penitents</hi> who had notoriouſly broken their <hi>Baptiſmal</hi> Vow, to their <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Eſtate,</hi> and Capacity again: it is not to me improbable, that the <hi>Candidates</hi> for <hi>both</hi> were enjoyned to appear in the <hi>ſame Garb,</hi> wherein the <hi>one</hi> ſort (by the Teſtimony of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity) were admitted to that <hi>Ordinance:</hi> from which Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the <hi>Dominica in Albis,</hi> which from the <hi>white Veſtments</hi> worn by the Baptiſed, on that ſolemn Day eſpecially appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anciently for the publick <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> thereof, ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with us, the Name of <hi>White ſunday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Digreſſion</hi> (if it be ſo to be accounted) on this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I thought fit to make, in order, if not to the Satisfaction, yet to the ſtopping the mouth of thoſe, who, (that they may diſcourage the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>publick Penance,</hi> ſo uſeful for the Souls of <hi>Penitents</hi> themſelves, and ſo conducible to the <hi>Cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,)</hi> have, in this laſt Age, endeavoured to <hi>Ridicu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> it; and I hope, it may not prove altogether unſucceſsful to the end intended.</p>
            <p>And now, (to conclude my <hi>Application</hi> to you;) remember what I told you, that the <hi>ſincere Conformity</hi> in your <hi>Hearts,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your <hi>outward Garb,</hi> in the <hi>Confeſſions</hi> you are now to make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your ſeveral Caſes, can only render you capable o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the benefit of that <hi>Abſolution,</hi> or <hi>Miniſterial Forgiveneſs</hi> which in the cloſe of this <hi>Action,</hi> I am impowered by the Church to give you, (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expreſſeth it, 2 Cor. 2. 10. in the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt:</hi> for without it, it will be beſtowed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>clave errnate,</hi> (as the <hi>Schools</hi> ſpeak) upon <hi>miſtaken Subjects</hi> and ſo prove not only <hi>Ineffectual,</hi> for you good, but alſo greatly <hi>Prejudicial</hi> to you, before him that <hi>ſearcheth the Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>tryeth the Reins,</hi> by the Addition of high <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and foul <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> to your <hi>other Crimes;</hi> which God of his Mercy give you Grace to prevent.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46829:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
